Dr.Patrick J. Nicholson Papers, 1933-1979
University of Houston Libraries
Dr. Patrick J. Nicholson Papers
1933-1979
Nicholson, Patrick James 1921-1999
Dr. Patrick James Nicholson the author of In Time: An Anecdotal History of the First Fifty Years of the University of Houston came to the University of Houston as a lecturer in Management in 1951. In 1956 he became Executive Director of Development and Assistant to the President and he was named Vice President of University Development in 1957, a position he maintained until his retirement in August of 1981. This collection includes correspondence, brochures, reports and newspaper articles concerning many university-related topics as well as a small amount of personal material.
21 boxes; 21 linear feet
1982-004
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Biographical Note
Dr. Patrick James Nicholson (1921-1999) is best known as the author of In Time: An Anecdotal History of the First Fifty Years of the University of Houston. He received a BA from Rice University in 1942, an MBA from Harvard in 1946, and a Ph.D., from the University of Houston in 1959. Nicholson came to the University of Houston as a lecturer in Management in 1951. He continued until 1956, when he became Executive Director of Development and Assistant to the President. He was named Vice President of University Development in 1957, a position he maintained until his retirement in August of 1981. Honorary positions Nicholson held included Past President of the American College Public Relations Association; Past President of the Houston Council on World Affairs; Past President of the Institute of Ophthalmology, Texas Medical Center; and N.Y. Academy of Sciences. He was a member of Phi Kappa Phi; Phi Eta Sigma; Sigma Xi; and Omicron Delta Kappa.
Scope and Contents
The Dr. Patrick J. Nicholson Papers consist of eleven records center cartons, one manuscript box and two oversized boxes. The collection includes correspondence, brochures, reports and newspaper articles concerning many university-related topics and a small amount of personal material. Some folders contain a variety of materials relating to that particular folder topic. Materials in the collection date from 1933 to 1979, with the majority dating from the mid-1960s to the mid-1970s.
The collection is divided into four series: Correspondence, University of Houston, Personal, and Oversize. The collection arrived in little discernible order and with little arrangement. An arrangement scheme has been imposed in consultation with the Archivist. For preservation reasons the collection has been re-boxed and re-foldered. New folder titles conform, as much as possible, to original folder titles. Exceptions were made when the folder title was obviously incomplete, incorrect, or confusing. Original item order has been preserved whenever possible.
Much of the collection concerns the University of Houston, or involves University of Houston groups, regardless whether the words "University of Houston" are part of the folder title. Topics relating to the University of Houston include the university in general, fundraising activities, history of the university, financial statements, and testimony before the Higher Education Commission, among many others. While the personal portion of the collection is relatively small, it has been maintained to provide background information and perspective to the researcher. It includes a variety of materials including Nicholson's dissertation. Additionally the collection contains an extensive range of newspaper articles relating to both UH and non-UH subjects.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Index Terms
Terms are either Library of Congress Subject Headings or taken from local sources.
Subjects(Persons)
Nicholson, Patrick James 1921-1999
Subjects (Organizations)
University of Houston; University of Houston History; University of Houston Administration
Formats
Correspondence; Reports; Agendas; Brochures; Clippings
Detailed Description
- Correspondence (Box 1-15)
  This series dates from 1958 through 1969, with one folder from 1976. It is the largest (fifteen boxes) and the strongest series within this collection. It consists of letters from Nicholson to a variety of people including donors, potential donors, and well-known associates of the university among others. The folders in this series cover a wide range of university related topics. Due to Nicholson's job responsibilities as Vice President of University Development, fundraising receives a strong emphasis within the correspondence series. Materials are arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, July 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, August 5-15, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, August 18-29, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, September 1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, October 1-15, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, October 16-31, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, November 3-13, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, November 17-26, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, December 1-16, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, December 17-31, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Ph.D. Dissertation, First Draft January 1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, January 5-29, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, February 2-19, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, February 20-27, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, March 2-13. 1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, March 16-30, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, April 1-14. 1959 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, April 15-30, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, May 1-14, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, May 18-30, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, June 2-15, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, June 16-30, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, July 1-13, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, July 16-31, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, August 1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, September 1-9, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, September 11-18, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, September 21-30, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, October 1-15, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, October 16-30, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, November 1-15, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, November 16-30, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, December 2-9, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, December 10-31, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, January 4-13, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, January 15-29, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, February 1-12, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, February 15-26, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, March 1-30, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, April 4-14, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, April 20-29, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, May 2-17, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, May 19-30, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, June 1-23, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, June 24-28, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, July 5-20, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, July 20-29, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, August 1-19, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, August 22-31, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, September 1-13, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, September 16-29, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, October 3-31, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, November 2-14, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, November 15-18, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, November 21-30, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, December 1-28, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, January 1961 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, February 1961 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, March 1961 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, April 1961 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, May 1961 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, June 1961 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, July 1961 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, August 1-11, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, August 14-31, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, September 5-8, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, September 11-14, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, September 15-20, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, September 21-29, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, October 2-13, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, October 16-31, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, November 1-13, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, November 14-30, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, December 1-11, 961 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, December 12-28, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, January 3-18, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, January 18-30, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, February 1-20, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, February 21-28, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, March 2-14, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, March 15-30, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, April 2-17, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, April 18, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, April 19, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, April 25-30, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, May 1-10, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, May 11-31, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, June 1-22, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, June 25-29, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, July 1962 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, August 1-7, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, August 8-31, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, September 1962 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, October 1-12, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, October 15-31, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, November 1-19, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, November 20-30, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, December 1962 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, January 3-17, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, January 18-31, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, February 1-20, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, February 21-28, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, March 1-8, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, March 12-29, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, April 1963 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, May 1963 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, June 1963 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, July 1-19, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, July22-30, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, August 1963 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, September 3-12, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, September 13-30, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, October 1-10, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, October 11-22, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, October 22-31, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, November 1-13, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, November 14-27, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, December 2-13, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, December 16-31, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, January 2-7, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, January 8-21, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, January 22-31, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, February 3-10, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, February 11-28, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, March 3-11, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, March 12-17, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, March 19-31, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, April 1-10, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, April 13-21, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, April 22-29, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, May 4-12, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, May 13-24, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, May 25-29, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, June 2-19, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, June 11-19, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, June 22-30, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, July 1-14, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, July 20-28, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, July 29-31, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, August 3-20, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, August 21-31, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, September 1-12, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, September 21-29, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, October 1-20, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, October 21-31, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, November 3-13, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, November 16-30, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, December 1-9, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, December 10-31, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, January 4-13, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, January 14-21, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January 25-31, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, February 1-12, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, February 15-19, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, February 22-26, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, March 1-2, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, March 2-4, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, March 4-16, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, March 16-18, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, March 19, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, March 19, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, March 19, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, March 25-29, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, April 1-13, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, April 15-22, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, April 22-29, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, May 3-20, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, May 21-28, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, June 1-8, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, June 9-16, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, June 17-30, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, July 1-21, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, July 22-30, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, August 1965 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, September 1-15, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, September 16-30, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, September 23-30, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, October 1-15, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, October 19-29, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Excellence Campaign Dinner UH Foundation Honoring Workers, November 15, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, November 1-10, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, November 11-23, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, November 24-29, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, December 1-10, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, December 13-31, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, January 3-12, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, January 13-26, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, February 1-11, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, February 14-28, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, March 1-11, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, March 14-22, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, March 23-31, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, April 1-15, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, April 15-22, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, April 26-29, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May 2-6, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, May 9-17, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, May 18-31, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, June 1-6, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, June 7-13, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, June 14-22, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, June 23-29, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, July 1-21, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, July 22-29, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, August 1-12, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, August 15, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, August 16-22, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, August 23-30, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, September 1-16, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, September 19-30, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, October 1-12, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, October 13-31, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, November 1-8, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, November 9-22, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, November 23-30, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, December 1-9, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, December 12-28, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, January 3-19, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, January 20-30, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, February 1-14, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, February 15-23, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, February 24-28, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, March 1-10, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, March 13-21, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, March 22-30, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Excellence Program Correspondence, March 20, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Excellence Program Correspondence, March 20, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Excellence Program Correspondence, March 23, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Excellence Program Correspondence, March 24, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Excellence Program Correspondence, March 28-29, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Excellence Program Correspondence, March 31, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, April 4-12, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, April 13-21, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, April 24-28, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May 1-9, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, May 10-12, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, May 15-23, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, May 24-25, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, May 26-29, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, May 30-31, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, June 1-9, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, June 12-30, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, July 1967 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, August 1-17, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, August 18-23, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, August 24-31, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, September 1-6, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, September 6, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, September 7-15, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, September 19-20, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, September 21-29, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, October 2-9, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, October 10-19, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, October 20-31, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, November 1-9, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, November 10-28, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, November 29-30, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, December 1-8, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, December 18-29, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Law Alumni Letters, December 15-20, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Law Alumni Letters, January 1968 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, January 3-11, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, January 11-25, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, January 26-31, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, February 2-8, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, February 9-20, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, February 21-29, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, March 1-18, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, March 19-28, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, April 1-2, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, April 2-15, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, April 16-30, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, May 1-7, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, May 8-21, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, May 21-31, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, June 3-11, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, June 12-19, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, June 20-28, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, July 1-9, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, July 10-15, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, July 16-23, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, July 24-31, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, August 1-15, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, August 16-30, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, September 3-11, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, September 13-24, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, September 25-30, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, October 1-7, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, October 8-17, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, October 18, 31, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, November 1-6, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, November 7-27, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, December 2-10, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, December 11-30, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Letters to Excellence Campaign Prospects, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Letters to Excellence Campaign Prospects, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Letters to Excellence Campaign Prospects, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Letters to Excellence Campaign Prospects, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Letters to Excellence Campaign Prospects, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Letters to Excellence Campaign Prospects, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Letters to Excellence Campaign Prospects, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Letters to Excellence Campaign Prospects, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence June to August, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Oct. 1965-Feb. 1969 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence Controversy, February-November 1969 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence Miscellaneous, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 12)
- University of Houston (Box 15-18)
  This series dates from the 1940s to 1979 and covers a wide range of materials and topics relating to the University of Houston. Types of materials include reports, studies, brochures, class notes, and articles. Topics range from building dedications and general history to testimony by university officials before various commissions. Also included in this series are page proofs for Nicholson's book In Time. Original folder titles have been maintained as much as possible. The materials in this series were in no discernable order and an order has been imposed in consultation with the Archivist. This series has been divided into five sub-series: General History, Financial Records, Development, Teaching, and Subject Files. In general the folders in each sub-series are arranged chronologically.
  - General History (Box 15, Folder 13-19)
    - folder 1 of 7, 1950s (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - folder 2 of 7, 1950s (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - folder 3 of 7, 1950s (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - folder 4 of 7, 1950s (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - folder 5 of 7, 1950s (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - folder 6 of 7, 1950s (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - folder 7 of 7, 1950s (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - Financial Records (Box 15, Folder 20-22)
    - Financial Statements, 1940s (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Financial Statements, 1950s (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - Financial Statements, 1960s (Box 15, Folder 22)
  - Development (Box 15, Folder 23-25)
    - Proposed Development Brochure, 1955 (Box 15, Folder 23)